<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true narrative of the confession and execution of Francis Nicholson who was executed this present Wednesday, being the 27th of this instant October, 1680. And hang'd up in chains at Hownslow-Heath, for murthering of one John Dimbleby at Hampton-Court this being his own true confession both to the Ordinary of Newgate, and several other ministers and others who came to him whilst he continued in prison, and have hereunto subscribed their names to attest the truth of this relation.</title>
            <author>Nicholson, Francis, d. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2777B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896022</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2374:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true narrative of the confession and execution of Francis Nicholson who was executed this present Wednesday, being the 27th of this instant October, 1680. And hang'd up in chains at Hownslow-Heath, for murthering of one John Dimbleby at Hampton-Court this being his own true confession both to the Ordinary of Newgate, and several other ministers and others who came to him whilst he continued in prison, and have hereunto subscribed their names to attest the truth of this relation.</title>
                  <author>Nicholson, Francis, d. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by D. Mallet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153678:1"/>
            <head>THE TRUE NARRATIVE OF THE CONFESSION AND EXECUTION Of <hi>Francis Nicholſon</hi> Who was Executed this preſent <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> being the 27th of this inſtant <hi>October,</hi> 1680. And Hang'd up in Chains AT Hownſlow-Heath, For Murthering of one John Dimbleby AT HAMPTON-COURT This being his own true Confeſſion both to the <hi>Ordinary</hi> of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> and ſeveral other Miniſters and others who came to him whilſt he continued in Priſon, and have hereunto ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed their Names to atteſt the Truth of this Relation.</head>
            <p>MY Father was a Malſter in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> who lived in good reputation, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is now a Widow, that liveth in credit and is well beloved, and they gave me good Education, but I was a diſobedient and unruly Son to a loving and tender Mother. I never heard of any of my Kindred that was guilty of Theft Murder, or any ſuch horrid Crimes before my ſelf, for which I have juſtly brought this death upon me, nor did I ever hear of any of my Relations that were ever caſt into any Goal or Priſon before.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153678:2"/>
            <p>My neglect of duty to my Mother, cauſed me to fall into the acquaintance of ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of other lude fellows in whom I took too much delight, and the more ſleighted the care and counſel of my Mother.</p>
            <p>By frequenting ſuch bad company I fell with them to drinking, and to ſpend my time and money vainly at the Alehouſe; though my Mother and Friends ſought to draw me from it, for the bad acquaintance I had prevailed more with me.</p>
            <p>And then we fell to breaking the Sabbath day, by our meeting at the Alehouſe, and other bad places, when we ſhould have been at Church ſerving God, to the grief of my tender Mother.</p>
            <p>And by theſe evil doings I got ſo bad an habit, that I grew careleſs how to put my ſelf into any way to live in any good courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>And being thus unſetled in my mind I did conſent to a young man of my unhappy acquaintance to joyn with him in ſtealing of an Horſe, for us to ride to <hi>London</hi> and ſeek for ſome imployment there.</p>
            <p>I had very little money to carry me up, and was too ſtubborn to ſeek to my Mother: but helping a Drover whom I overtook with Beaſts, I had Diet and Lodging in my journey till I came to <hi>London</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>But I had money and neceſſaries ſent after me, by my Mother to <hi>London,</hi> of which I was very glad for I knew not what courſe to take</p>
            <p>And then I put my ſelf Apprentice to a Carpenter a very honeſt good man, who was a loving Maſter to me; and gave me good edueation, and was a loving Maſter to me and to whom <hi>I</hi> was much obliged for his care of me, and well pleaſed with his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>And though he had divers pieces of Plate about the houſe, and other good Goods yet <hi>I</hi> did never wrong him of any thing by any Theft or Pilfering.</p>
            <p>But <hi>I</hi> robbed both God and my Maſter of too much time with naughty company that <hi>I</hi> found out, in drinking, and merry meeting, and lewdneſs, and ſin.</p>
            <p>And <hi>I</hi> did greatly profane the Sabbath day by neglecting the Church, and meeting with my acquaintance, walking about and ſitting in an Alehouſe, and a very bad life, ſo that <hi>I</hi> have ſome times thus ſpent the whole Sabbath day, from nine a clock in the morning until midnight, and then have come home drunk.</p>
            <p>And in all this I was not ſenſible of my miſerable condition, by thus provoking God by my Sins, in which it was Gods mercy to ſpare me, and give me time to repent had I had grace to have improved it.</p>
            <p>But that which is moſt dreadful upon my Conſcience is, this bloody Fact for which I am to die, which lieth as a very ſore and heavy burden upon my Soul; and for which I can give no reaſon why I did it, but the inſtigation of the Devil tempting to it when I was drunk, and not having the fear of God before mine Eyes, and my Senſes gone with drink, I was thus overcome of Satan, and took up my Hatchet, and (oh my Soul bleeds to think of it) I murdered that man that never did me injury.</p>
            <p>I was there at work for my Maſter, and had opportunity (being from home) to ſpend my time more ill, and not having God in my thoughts, I lived profane and lewdly.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>I</hi> can ſay (<hi>I</hi> thank God) <hi>I</hi> never did commit Whoredom with any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but ill company, Sabbath-breaking, drunkenneſs, diſobedience to Parents, profaneſs, and other Sins <hi>I</hi> have been deeply guilty of. The Lord be merciful to me, and pardon and forgive me for the ſake of my dear Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>When I had committed this horrid Murder for which I am to die, there was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther young man that was ſuſpected to have done it, and was apprehended upon that ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>But when upon further inquiry <hi>I</hi> was found out (by a Watch <hi>I</hi> took out of his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket) to be the man that did it; <hi>I</hi> was apprehended, and confeſſed that it was <hi>I</hi> that murdered him.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>I</hi> was asked if the other young man in cuſtody upon ſuſpition, did not joyn with me, or hire me, or ſet me on do it, and whether he had not ſome hand with me in it.</p>
            <p>To which I (like a wicked Wretch) affirmed that he hired me, and promiſed to give me forty ſhillings, and a better thing; and ſo he came to be indicted with me, and put in danger of his Life.</p>
            <p>But this wrong that I did to him hath much troubled me, and I thank God that the Jury did acquit him: And though he was acquitted, yet I could not be quiet in my mind till I ſent for him, and I thank him that he came to me, and when he came to me, I heartily asked him forgiveneſs, and he hath as freely forgiven me.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153678:2"/>
            <p>Since I have been condemned to die, I have been much troubled in Conſcience for all my-ſinful and naughty Life, eſpecially for this bloody and wicked murder, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great terror to me, fearing leſt God will not pardon ſo vile a Sin, yet not deſpairing, ſo that I have been greatly dejected; and my Soul dead, ſtupified, under the terror and wrath of God, not knowing what to do.</p>
            <p>But ſince the help I have had from the Ordinary, and other godly Miniſters, who have conferred with me, and prayed with me, and for me and inſtructed me out of Gods word, both together with other condemned Priſoners, and privately with my ſelf, (the Lord requite them for their great pains) I have found ſome hopes of mercy from God through Chriſt Jeſus my Saviour, who died for me, which I prize more than my life. I am very ſenſible of Gods mercies to me, a wicked wretch that deſerve not what I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy received, though like a wicked unthankful creature I have not improved but abuſed them heretofore, but do now in deep ſenſe of them, magnifie Gods goodneſs therein. I confeſs it is a great mercy from God to me (praiſed be his holy Name) that my life hath not been cut off in the midſt of the very act of Sins, and been caſt into Hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ever, but that God ſpared me and gave me time to repent; and offered me the bleſſed means and helps that I have found here in Priſon. I confeſs it is Gods great mercy to me (by means of thoſe worthy Miniſters that have viſited me) to aſſiſt, teach, counſel, and comfort me in the way of peace, and reconciliation with God through Chriſt; in which I have found a great change in me and hope of mercy. I confeſs that it is a great mercy and favour to me to move the heart of the Recorder and others that have given me ſo long time of repentance, after the ſentence of Death paſſed upom me, before my Execution too, methinks I find my heart dayly more and more humbled, my ſorrow for my Sins to encreaſe, and my hopes of mercy and pardon of my ſins, and of the ſalvation of my Soul move more lively in me. And I thank the Lord that by his providence and grace, he hath under this ſad diſpenſation of Death, brought my mind into a willing and hearty ſubmiſſion to his Will.</p>
            <p>I am not troubled that I muſt die in ſubmiſſion to Gods providence, I do not much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to live any longer, only to ſettle my peace with God, hoping when I die, through Gods mercy to enjoy Life Eternal through Jeſus Chriſt my Saviour. It is not Life in this World, nor any thing of this Life that I wraſtle with God for; I thank God I hang looſe to all Worldly things. But it is the mercy of God to my Soul, and the blood of Chriſt to waſh away my ſins, and to ſave my Soul that I labour for, peace of Conſcience and Eternal Life that I earneſtly ſeek for. Oh my ſins, my Sins, theſe are my ſorrows, therefore I beg unto God day and night in the dark Dungeon where I lie in Fetters of Iron, what ever the Lord doth with me in this Life and what ever I ſuffer, that my ſins may be pardoned and that my poor ſinful ſoul may be ſaved, and I do hope to find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from God, who hath promiſed mercy to thoſe that confeſs their ſins and repent and call upon him, and though my ſins are very great, yet my comfort is that his mercies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more and are greater than my ſins, and the mercies of God towards me aad his great working upon me ſince I have been condemned, makes me alſo to hope that the Lord intends in mercy to ſave me though I have been ſo great a ſinner. I do ſpend my time in my diſmal Dungeon I thank God in much prayer in which I find great Comfort from God to my Soul, and ſequeſtring my thoughts from the things of this world that I may more comfortably injoy God. I deſire all young men to take warning by me, that you may not bring the wrath of God upon you in the like Judgment that I am under, or ſome other as dreadful or more bitter. Had I been Dutiful to my Parents I had not needed to have taken ſuch deſperate Courſes as I have done. Had I kept the Sabbath holy I had not fallen in ſuch lewd profane company as have brought me to this miſerable end. Had I not been drunk I had not committed this horrid Murder. And had I refrained ill company I had not lain under ſo great temptations to Sin. Had I had grace and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom I might have lived as comfortably and as happily as others of my degree. Had I been dutiful to a careful Mother, or obedient to a good Maſter, I had not come to this ſad end, but might have lived to have ſeen happy days. I pray God I may be a warning to all Children to teach them duty to their Parents, to all Apprentices to teach them to mind firſt their duty to God, and then the Buſineſs they are intruſted by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. And to all young Men to take heed of ill Company, ſuch as delight to Sin: To all Sabbath-breakers to amend and turn to God, leſt he leave them to Satan and they fall into ſome dreadful Sin. And to all Drunkards, whoſe ſin therein maketh them Slaves to Satan to commit any deſperate wickedneſs that he tempts them to.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>This is truly my Confeſſion, witneſs my Hand <hi>Francis Nichollſon.</hi> Witneſs <hi>H. Walker,</hi> Miniſter. <hi>Richard Paxton, Richard Hawker,</hi> Officers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153678:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Confeſſion of <hi>Francis Nicholſon to</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> Ordinary of <hi>Newgate, in</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his Murthering of <hi>John Dimbleby.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FRancis Nicholſon</hi> declared voluntarily, and at ſeveral times to me Mr. <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> Ordinary of <hi>Newgate,</hi> and to divers other perſons then preſent, that he the ſaid <hi>Nicholſon</hi> was not hired by the Perſon Arraigned with him, to commit the ſaid Murther, as he perſiſted to affirm at his Trial, but the ſaid Aſſeveration was his meer contrivance, to leſſen his own Crime, And farther did Relate, that he had never thought of the Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, had not the man at the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> asked him the queſtion when he was before the Juſtice whether or no the Coachman was not concerned with him. ſaying ſurely ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt ſet him on to do it, and thinking thereby to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, was the only reaſon of his charging of the Coachman with that bloody Act. Whereupon I <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> told him that he ought to ſend for the Perſon he had ſo wronged and to beg his Pardon, which ſince he hath done.</p>
            <p>After the Diſcovery of ſuch a falſe Aſperſion, I ask'd the ſaid <hi>Nicholſon,</hi> what moved him to murther the perſon, he ſaid that having drank hard one Night in Company, he wiſht that God would damn him if he did not try to kill a Man, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from that very time, for a fortnight together, the Devil did ſo haunt him, that he had no reſt in his mind, by the Tempters urging him to make good his Vow, for otherwiſe he would be certainly Damned. He ſaid that it was indifferent to him whom he killed, ſo he killed ſome Body to eaſe his mind. That he watcht an opportunity to kill the perſon at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> but his heart failed him ſeveral times, yet being left to himſelf, by God for his wicked imprecation or wiſh, he was ſo hurried on by the Devil to effect that Murthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that he could not withſtand it for he declared to me ſeveral times that it neither proceeded from any Grudg or Malice, nor hope of Gain, yet after he had killed the Man, he ſearcht his Pockets and took out a Watch; alſo he ſaid to me that this troubles his Conſcience very much, that he killed the Man on a ſudden, and ſo dying without prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he knows not in what ſtate or Condition his Soul is in.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ita Teſtor, Samuel Smith</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>D. Mallet,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
